Register of the Franz Schoenberner Papers, 1899-1970
Hoover Institution Archives
Franz Schoenberner Papers,
1899-1970
72020
Schoenberner, Franz, 1892-
4 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope, 1 phonotape reel 1.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Writings and correspondence, relating to German literature, national socialism in Germany, and anti-Nazi German émigré life
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1972.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Nationalsozialistische deutsche Arbeiter-Partei; Simplicissimus; Anti-Nazi movement; Germans in foreign countries; National socialism; Refugees; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945--France; France; Germany; Germany--History--20th century; Germany--Intellectual life; Phonotapes; Journalists
Biographical Note
Schoenberner, Franz, 1892-1970
1892, December 18 Born, Berlin, Germany
1929-1933 Editor, Simplicissimus, German satirical magazine
1933 Fled to France, Commune de Roquebrune-Cap Martin
1941 Emigrated to the United States
1943 Editor, Office of War Information
1946 Confessions of a European Intellectual (autobiography)
1949 The Inside Story of an Outsider (sequel to autobiography)
1951 Assaulted, almost completely paralyzed
1957 You Still Have Your Head: Excursions of Immobility
1965 First return to Germany
1968 Der Weg der Vernunft und andere Aufsaetze (Published and unpublished writings by Schoenberner, 1933ff., including Family Portraits.)
1970 Died, New Jersey
Series Description
- Writings. (Box Box No. 1 -3.)
  Manuscripts to books, articles, and lectures, written in English, German, or French.
- Correspondence. (Box Box No. 3 -4.)
  Correspondence, 1899-1970, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
- Miscellany. (Box Box No. 4.)
  Certificates, affidavits, identification cards, etc.
Container List
- Writings
  - Confessions of A European Intellectual, 1946. (Box 1.)
  - The Inside Story of an Outsider, 1949.
  - The Dilemma of Modern Liberalism. English and German copies. (Box 2.)
  - The Adventure of Reading Goethe's Novel `Wilhelm Meister's Apprenticeship'. English and German copies.
  - Article from L'Age Nouveau, Jan. 1939. German copy.
  - Beware of False Prophets. English and German copies.
  - Haben die Deutschen Humor? German copy.
  - Faith and Scepticism, published in Euros, Amsterdam, May, 1965. English and German copies.
  - German Literature in Exile. English and German copies.
  - The German Language Shall Never Parish from the Earth. Lecture. English and German copies.
  - Why Intellectuals are Treasonable, published in Tomorrow, New York, 1943. English and German copies.
  - Stefan Zweig and We, published in The New Republic, March 1942. English and German copies.
  - Facts and Opinions, published in The Protestant, Sept. 1944. English and German copies.
  - Goethe Revival. English copy.
  - Roman und Film im Kampf gegen Rassenvorurteile. German copy.
  - Innocents from Abroad. English copy.
  - The Paradox of Katherine Anne Porter. English copy.
  - Speaking of German Literature. English copy.
  - What's the Matter with France? German copy.
  - North Africa - A Test Case. English copy.
  - Begegnung mit D.H. Lawrence. German copy.
  - Apropos of Blasphemy, published in abbreviated form in The Reporter, January 1951. English and German copies.
  - Das Nibelungenlied. German copy.
  - Dokumente amerikanischer Demokratie. German copy.
  - Die deutschen Zeitschriften des Departments of the Army. Germany copy.
  - Georges Bernanos: Nous autres Francais, published in Decision, 1941? German copy.
  - Lektuere fuer die Hitler-Jugend. German copy.
  - Mes heures avec Leon Souguenet. French copy.
  - Family Portraits, including biographical notes, photos, and his mother's school essays, report cards, and diaries. English and German copies.
  - Life and Death of `Simplicissimus'. Proposal for a book based on selected cartoons from Simplicissimus.
  - Letter to The New Republic and to The New York Times. An Answer to Arthur Koestler's `Challenge to Knights in Rusty Armor.' English copy.
  - Letter to PM, April 1943, on Frank Sullivan's article Sullivan Backs up and Lets go. English and German copies.
  - How to Treat Inflated Mr. Ludwig? Reply to Emil Ludwig's letter on Mussolini and Ethiopia, December 1943, and Ludwig's answer. English copy.
  - Letter to The New York Times Book Review, July 1950, on Alvin Kugelmass' Literary Letter from Germany. English copy.
  - Letter to Freda Kirchwey, editor of The Nation, March 1951, protesting against an article by Alexander Werth on Andre Gide. German copy.
  - Letter to Atlantic Monthly regarding article by Brickner Is Germany Incurable? English and German copies.
  - Letter to Saturday of Literature, August 1941, challenging the author of The Fall of the House of Ullstein. English and German copies.
  - Evaluations for American publishers of primarily German books: (Box 3.)
    - Amery, Jean. Geburt der Gegenwart (Gestalten und Gestaltungen der westlichen Zivilisation seit Kriegsende)
    - Bychowski, Gustav. Dictators and Disciples: from Caesar to Stalin.
    - Bamm, Peter. An den Kuesten des Lichts.
    - Bauer, Paul. Kampf um den Himalaja.
    - Bloemertz, Gunther. Dem Himmel am naechsten.
    - Buddenbrock, W.v. Die Welt der Sinne.
    - Bertram, Hans. Flug zu den Sternen.
    - Bauer, Walter. Besser zu zweit als allein.
    - Bergengruen, Werner. Das Feuerzeichen.
    - Clerque, S. Ch. Rettet unsere Seelen.
    - Cappon, Joseph. Dolorosa.
    - Furtwaengler, Wilhelm. Gespraeche uber Musik.
    - Glas, Simon. Das Netz.
    - Heinrich, Willi. The Cross of Iron.
    - Jucker, Ernst. Sibiriens Waelder raunen.
    - Jens, Walter. The Blind Man.
    - Kramer, Gerhard. Wie werden weiter marschieren.
    - Koeppen, Wolfgang. Tauben im Gras.
    - Kern, Erick. Menschen im Netz.
    - Kuhn, Herbert. Die Felsbilder Europas; Die Kunst Alt-Europas.
    - Lichnowsky, Mechtilde. Kindheit.
    - Lissner, Ivar. So habt Ihr gelebt.
    - Johnson, Eyvind. Hier hast du dein Leben; Traeume von Rosen und Feuer.
    - Marai, Alexander. Begegnung in Bolzano.
    - Nasemann, Richard. Nasses Brot.
    - Rainalter, Erwin H. Der Sandwirt, Der Roman Andreas Hofers.
    - Rinser, Luise. Mitte des Lebens.
    - Schaper, Edzard. Der letzte Advent.
    - Schneider, Reinhold. Imperial Mission.
    - Stanley, Ilse. The Unforgotten.
    - Steiger, Otto Die Reise ans Meer.
    - Tanzer, Franz. Die Befreiung.
    - Thelen, Albert Vigoleis. Die Insel des zweiten Gesichts; Aus den angewandten Errinerungen des Vigoleis.
    - Torberg, Friedrich. Die zweite Begegnung.
  - Book reviews, written by Franz Schoenberner (typescripts and clippings):
    - Abegg, Lilly. Ostasien denkt anders.
    - Boeschenstein, H. The German Novel, 1939-1944.
    - Bierman, Berthold. Goethe's world as seen in his letters and memoirs.
    - Freud, Sigmund. Leonardo da Vinci, a psychoanalytical study.
    - Hersey, John. The Wall (in German).
    - Guerard, Albert. Education of a Humanist.
    - Heinrich, Willi. The Cross of Iron.
    - Kaufmann, Richard. Der Himmel zahlt keine Zinsen.
    - Kesten, Hermann. Ferdinand and Isabella.
    - Kreuder, Ernst. Die Unauffindbaren.
    - Mahler, Alma. Gustav Mahler.
    - Moore, Harry T. D.H. Lawrence's letters to Bertrand Russell.
    - Lewisohn, Ludwig. Goethe, the Story of a Man.
    - Nehru, Pandit S.S. Gandhi, sein Leben und Werk.
    - Pribilla, Max. Deutsche Schicksalsfragen.
    - Roepke, Wilhelm. The Solution of the German Problem.
    - Schweitzer, Albert. Goethe, Four Studies.
    - Vercors. Three Short Novels.
    - Waugh, Coulton. The Comics.
    - Weigand, Hermann J. Goethe: Wisdom and Experience.
    - 3 books about and 3 books by Albert Schweitzer.
    - von Salomon, Ernst. Die Geaechteben.
  - Book reviews of F. Schoenberner's books and other publications.
- Correspondence
  - A (Box 3.)
  - B
  - Bemelmans, Ludwig
  - Bertillon, Suzanne
  - C
  - Capouya, Emile
  - Congrat-Butlar, Stefan
  - Covici, Friede, Inc., N.Y.
  - Cusack, Ralph
  - D
  - Depicnis (?), Caillons
  - Department of State group (Germans in exile)
  - E
  - Einstein, Albert
  - Eissler, Ruth S.
  - F
  - Fleetwealth, Alistair
  - Francheschi, M. de
  - G
  - Graff, William G.
  - Gulbransson, Olaf
  - H
  - Harper & Row, New York
  - Heine, Thomas Th.
  - Hermann. Lutz (Deutsche Zeitung)
  - Hirschberg, Emma
  - Hirschberg, Martin
  - K
  - Kadach, Wilhelmine Eleanore
  - Kesten, Hermann, German novelist and playwright, present president of PEN German Center in Frankfurt (47 letters, 4 postcards and 1 telegram, 1941-1953).
  - Knoll, Paul
  - Kohn, Hein
  - Kramer, Walter A.
  - Kreisselmeier, Hermann. Correspondence (1963-1969) with Hermann Kreisselmeier Verlag, Munich, Germany, Franz Shoenberner's German publisher
  - L
  - Latham, Harold S. (Vice President of The Macmillan Co.)
  - Lawrence, D.H.
  - Lawrence, Frieda
  - Lichnowsky, Mechtilde, writer and artist, widow of the former German ambassador in London, Prince Lichnowsky (approximately 74 handwritten letters and 12 postcards, 1933-1939) (Box 4.)
  - Life
  - M
  - Mann, Golo
  - Mann, Heinich
  - Mann, Klaus
  - Mhe, Herbert
  - Moore, Harry T.
  - N
  - The New Republic
  - The New School
  - New York Herald Tribune
  - Niebuhr, Reinhold
  - O
  - Overstreet, Harry A.
  - P
  - Paulding, Governor
  - Pfeiffer, Ernst
  - R
  - Regler, Gustav
  - Rheinhardt, E.A.
  - Roberts, Harley M.
  - Rode, Helen
  - Rode, Walther
  - Romain, Jules
  - S
  - Salzmann, Karl H.
  - Scheller, Hans
  - Scherz Verlag, Stuttgart, Germany
  - Schickele, Lannatsch
  - Schickele, Rene, novelist and poet, playwright and essayist (30 handwritten letters, 1935-1939, including 3 letters addressed to him)
  - Schoenberner, Gerhard (nephew)
  - Schoenberner family (Gudrun and Martha)
  - Seemann, Verlag Erich, G.M.B.H.
  - Shirer, William L.
  - Sinclair, Upton
  - Der Spiegel
  - T
  - Trautsehold, Lolo (approximately 36 mainly handwritten letters from and to L. Trautsehold, 1945-1949)
  - W
  - Wengraf, Fritz
  - Wertheim, Werner S.
  - Wisbeck, August
  - Wissenschaft und Politik, Verlag, Cologne, Germany
  - Wolff, Kurt
  - Z
  - Die Zeit
  - Zoff, Otto
  - Zweig, Stefan
  - Schoenberner's personal correspondence
  - Unidentified correspondence
  - Miscellaneous correspondence
- Miscellany
  - Certificates, affidavits, identification cards, etc. 1 tape of Franz Schoenberner's voice translating his own Confessions of a European Intellectual into German., 10.Rr. (Box 4.)